in today's tutorial we're gonna turn this
3d view into this 3d view there is a few
different ways we can do this in this tutorial
i'm just going to do the basics which is doing
a 3d view on the GrandMA 3 on pc itself you
can network two computers if you need more real
estate to program on one computer and see your
3d view and another one or you can network a
real GrandMA 3 console to a computer and that way
you can use the second computer as a visualizer
in this tutorial we are just going to do it on
the on pc version itself in a later tutorial i
will explain all the networking possibilities
you have on the GrandMA 3 console if you feel
like something is missing or there's something
you need to know please leave a comment below
in the comment section and i will
try to explain it as good as i can
so here we are i started a small sequence now
so we can see what we're doing i added a gobo to
the vipers and i just turned on the the macaroons
here in blue and then all my dimmers just pointing
up in the air so right now we're going to play
with the quality of the rendering right now the
rendering is pretty much standard that means this
is the rendering you're gonna see on the console
if you if you use a console you can't set the the
quality as high as we're gonna do now because the
console is gonna use too many resources on it so
if you want the high quality and you're working on
a real GrandMA 3 console you have to attach
a computer to the console to make sure that
you can do your rendering there and and the
computer can prioritize the rendering and the
console can prioritize what it's supposed to do
well let's start up let's go up here into the
MA button up here and push it and here we have
all the settings for the for the 3d view itself
we have some beam options when you
turn up and down the beam options the
beams are getting brighter and if you turn it all
the way down they're just going to disappear and
you can only see the footprint the same with
the spot you can turn the spot down this is
the footprint on the floor you can turn it up you
can turn it down depending on what you want to do
i'm just going to keep these two at about a
hundred percent but if you have some special need
you can just put it up or down so it fits your
need the ambient light is the light in the room in
here you can turn the ambient light down it gets
darker in the room and if you do the point light
as well it's going to be black i need a little
bit of ambient light in here otherwise we can't
we can't see the surroundings now here we have
beam quality if you push this one uh you will
have a lot of different options if you right click
you can see all the different options you have
so right now we're just gonna set it to the
highest options we can so high shadow fancy is the
one we selected right now the spot quality down
here if you right click again you can see we use
gobo and the bloom incentive is set to on right
now this is already helping a lot on the quality
if we go into the miscellaneous tab we can see
right now that we can't see any frames per second
this is important if your computer is not so
powerful then you can see how much you're pushing
it the lower the frame rate goes my screen
is only a 60 hertz screen so it can't go any
higher but it's it's around 60 frames per second
which is which is fine you can turn on wireframe
if you want to make it really simple this is how
it looked on the GrandMA 2 on the console itself
but what we need to do especially if you attach a
computer to the console itself you can set the 3d
priority if you set the 3d priority to the console
if you turn that on the console is going to use up
all its energy on rendering the view here and
not on what it's supposed to do calculating all
the dmx values but since we are on a on pc right
now we can just turn on the 3d priority like this
and it's going to ask you are you sure you
want to enable 3d priority and we just say yes
so right now if we are in a network and we have
multiple consoles and multiple ma computers
running the same software we can set one of
them or two of them or whatever you want to do
to have the 3d priority so it's going to do the
calculation and and leave the heavy lifting of the
dmx calculation to the to the console in
here we have some other options lens shading
we can turn that on and we have some
separated beams here and again if you
right click you can see all the options you
have and we say single beam dynamic gobo
we can move into label a label i showed you in
the last episode and if you missed that one by
the way how to set up your 3d view view how to
position all your fixtures in the 3d universe
check out episode four i'm gonna link to the
episode right up in the top hand corner and by the
end of the video i'm gonna link to the playlist so
you can see all the GrandMA 3 tutorial videos
in here we have some labels we can put a label
on the body if we want to know which fixtures are
where and then we can see okay what do we want to
see right now right now we see the fixture handle
we can turn on the the cid which doesn't have
any right now we can turn on the patch to see
where are they patched the different spots and if
they have a name if you named them right you can
see the name as well and you can turn on all of
them and then you can't see anything so basically
i just need to fix your id when i work with it
but in the 3d view i don't want to see the label
right here you have the we'll just turn it on
again the background alpha you can turn that down
and that means the the the label gets transparent
and if you do the other one the text
itself is going to be transparent
into the quality tab again you have some different
options if you can if you take this up or down
you take this all the way down you can see the
the resolution on the footprint is going to be
distorted if you take it all the way up to 100
again it's going to be much more sharp and it's
going to use more resources to render that view
the light scale i don't really see any difference
but if you uh maybe there's a difference in
the footprint yeah there is there's a small
difference in the footprint you see it's it's
once again it's out of focus it's more distorted
and the same here how many pixels you're going
to use in the shadows i don't see much of a
difference right here so this is basically how you
set up your 3d view and turn up the quality of the
view itself if you find it interesting please give
the video a like and otherwise you can check out
the next video it's on the playlist right here
in the top or the next video down in the bottom
thank you for watching and i hope to see
you next time on my channel thank you bye